Venkata Matcha

■ mvs.teja91@gmail.com □ 7579942295 https://www.linkedin.com/in/mvsteja91/

SUMMARY

Graduate Research Assistant pursuing a Master's in CS at Old Dominion University, Norfolk, VA, with 8 years of experience in Es6, CSS, Jenkins, React, Angular, MySQL, MongoDB, Flutter, and React-Native. A Senior Front End Developer with extensive knowledge and expertise seeking a challenging opportunity to create a better UI/UX experience.

SKILLS

Technical Skills: React JS, Redux, Spring Boot, Flutter, Angular 2, Bootstrap, Material UI, Highcharts, Java, Nodejs, React Native, Ember Js, Swift, IOS, Xcode, Charles Proxy, Flutter

EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant

August 2021 - May 2023

Old Dominion University, Norfolk, Va

- Developed user-friendly interfaces utilizing React Native and React for UI, Nginx for multi-app hosting, and a backend in Java's Spring boot.
- Built a feature-rich flutter app with features such as stripe payments and a BLOC pattern implementation.
- Made significant enhancements to a restaurant ordering mobile app built in Swift and storyboards.
- Solved the recurring dates problem in a Room Booking System for ODU.
- Implemented advanced features such as Elastic Search on large datasets, two-factor authentication, and password reset through email. Responsible for periodic data exports from SQL to Elastic search.
- Created a microservices architecture, utilizing SpringBoot-based services that interact through REST and SpringBoot.
- · Hands-on experience with MongoDB, including concepts such as locking, transactions, indexes, replications, and schema design.
- Experience troubleshooting application runtime issues by accessing Linux servers and viewing application logs through ssh.

Summer Internship Jun 2022 - Aug 2022

Map communications, Chesapeake, VA

- Successfully designed and implemented a Call Center System with advanced features such as agent login/logout, call transfer, and secure real-time voice communication, resulting in improved customer satisfaction and efficiency. This system was used by over 3,000 users, leading to a 65% decrease in customer complaints, a 15% increase in customer satisfaction, and a 25% improvement in call handling speed.
- Implemented application data pagination, search, and form filter functions based on queryDSL of the Java Spring framework.
- Deployed and managed Git branches through CI/CD pipelines in GitLab.

Senior Software Engineer

November 2018 - August 2021

Freshworks, Chennai, India

- Successfully transferred plotly components to highcharts, using Jest and Enzyme for unit testing. The migration was done one chart at a time with tests run across all product-specific components, resulting in an acceleration of chart rendering time by 91%, an improvement of test coverage from 42% to 82%, and a decrease in unit test execution time by 85%.
- Designed and developed a Freshworks CRM outlook add-in using React and TypeScript, along with Microsoft's UI Fluent library.
- Installed Spring boot-based microservices in Docker containers using Amazon EC2 Container Services and managed a team to develop and deploy a distributed Jenkins cluster on Kubernetes.
- Enhanced the performance of Mysql database queries by optimizing the database resources, including server performance, shared memory, and buffer pool size for seamless operation with distributed databases.
- Participated in Appathon 2019 by coding the UI for an Interactive Assistant for Freshworks CRM, utilizing speech-to-text recognition and text-to-speech translation interfaces using browser-built speech and text APIs.

Senior Associate August 2013 - November 2018

Cognizant technology solutions, Chennai, India

- Migrated a Flash client Application to React SPA.
- Primary tasks are leading the team's efforts on creating and improving jest enzyme test cases. Secondary tasks were to develop the Books tab, consisting of customizable search, Filtering/Sorting of collection, and Quiz management.
- Migrated build system from Webpack 1 to Webpack 3.
- Set up route-based code-splitting of application code. Introduced caching of static assets, (JS, CSS). Improved the landing page's time to first paint, Reducing the time to first interactive by 30%.
- Involved with Jest snapshot and unit testing, Integrated pre-commit scripts. Improved security and accessibility of the web app.
- Built a local mock web server based on Node JS and Express JS. This helped bridge the gap in API service availability thus improving the productivity of the team by 30%.

EDUCATION

Master in Science

Old Dominion University • Norfolk, VA • 2023 • 3.6

Bachelor of Technology

Indian Insitute of Information Technology • Chennai, India • 2012 • 6.37